MITOKO, ALFRED ODUOR

Po Box 49 – 40602 Ndori, Siaya County, Kenya

Cell: +254 720 476 821 jakaburatek@gmail.com Marital status: married

Career Summary

I am a quality focused manufacturing engineer with a wide range of technical skills on FMCG production and machine maintenance gained through experience in a span of seven years.

I have been in management and leadership team for a period of four years which has elevated my production and operation knowledge as well as maintenance practical experience. This enables my full contribution to management decision making as well as implementation of the same.

Achievements

Problem-solving skills.

I have been able to analyze machine challenges and resolve them through GO SEE THINK DO process, where our Earbuds machine had low output and of poor quality.

This resulted to an increase in production output by 80%

Creativity

I upgraded our tissue paper machine manufacturers design to suit our local needs from fixed small roll production capacity to doing a bigger roll as well. This helped in increasing our market product range by two standard keeping units.

Designing

I designed and supervised the fabrication, installation and commissioning of a withering trough fan silencer at Unilever Tea East Africa – Mabroukie factory as my attachment project.

I also introduced double sprocket coupling in our machines line shafts which eliminated breakdowns associated with the former fixed jaw coupling by 80%. This increased our current monthly capacity by 15% with a rise in quality by 0.5%

Key Skills

- Excellent communication skills, both written and spoken, and the ability to make technical aspects of engineering clearer to all variety of people.
- Ability to work well under pressure I have been in multiple occasions tasked to attend conflicting priorities, I always remain calm and tackle them one by one in order of urgency and providing guidance to my juniors. This has helped greatly in our general lead time reduction.
- Good time management, organizational and forward planning skills.
- Excellent understanding of maintenance, production and product quality aspects both theoretically, learned at college and practically, gained through application experience.
- Good at implementing development plans and checking on progress while supervising a team.
- I excel at maximizing equipment use, throughput and yields while minimizing on off specification products, through provision of training and guidance to workers to meet set performance standards.

Professional Experience

2020 April (current)

Plant Engineer

- Planning, organizing, implementing and overseeing day to day operations of the plant production and maintenance ensuring maximum value to all stakeholders.
- Managing cross functional activities in the plant through improved team cohesion geared at achieving the overall business objective. Leading, coordinating and monitoring a highly skilled team and guiding them on target achievements.
- Implementing strategies in line with corporate strategic initiatives, providing clear sense of direction and focus in achieving the overall organizational vision.
- Ensuring standard operation procedures are followed. Developing processes that will maximize product quality and productivity from the employees.
- Devising strategies of increasing machines efficiencies and ensuring that our target OEE of 75% is always achieved in our monthly operations with a utilization of over 80%
- Collecting and analyzing data to find available GAPs in our processes with an aim of optimizing the processes in our lean manufacturing strategy.
- Controlling process wastes, planning utilization of the available resources and ensuring highest quality standard of goods produced for a better overall market perception and customer satisfaction.
- Ensuring optimal and efficient operation of utility plants such as borehole and water distribution systems, wastewater treatment bio digesters, standby electric generators and air compressors
- Implementing cost reduction initiatives such as modification of various problematic machine parts to suit our production requirement minimizing plant maintenance and labor expenses.
- Carried out spare parts analysis and resourcing through proper planning and organized approach towards spare parts stocking. This has helped in reducing downtime on replacements and managed overstocking of spares resulting in low inventory cost.

2017 April – 2020 March Plant Assistant Manager/Engineer African Cotton Industries Limited

- Management of machine breakdowns prevention of breakdowns through proactive maintenance, allocation of resources in case breakdowns occur, maintaining relevant past breakdowns data for trend establishment and solution development.
- Through following best maintenance practices and application of Kaizen and 5s, I have contributed majorly in raising our OEE from 45.1% to 76.6% in a span of six months.
- Planning and supervising the installation and commissioning of new production lines with an aim of handing over a smooth operating machines to the production team.
- Managed projects from inception to completion some of which has led to reduced labor and operation cost in our production department. Case example being the automation of our log cutting machine which has raised our blade capacity from 32,000 bales to 50,000 bales per blade.
- Setting up rules and regulations regarding machine maintenance and safety. Ensuring that the standard operating procedures are adhered to by the involved staff which has helped reduce machine related accidents.

- Manage employee trainings on best maintenance practices such as RCM, CBM and required documentation which ensures machines run smoothly with the best quality of products realized.
- Ensuring that data on machine spares consumption is accurately collected and analyzed which has helped in checking machine efficiency and identification of machines that need improvement.
- Training of operators on good manufacturing practice and autonomous maintenance and SMED with additional skills on machine maintenance. This has helped in reducing maintenance team, helpers and production lead time consequently reducing our yearly overall labor cost by Ksh. 720,000 and faster changeovers.
- Subcontracting of qualified personnel for activities that requires specialized treatment which is
 out of reach of our resource capacity. Supervising the subcontractors to ensure we get value for
 money out of the service they offer.

2013 - 2017

Maintenance Assistant

African Cotton Industries Limited

- Installed new machines and aligned them to the production requirements through fine tuning of their setups. This enabled quick machine operation dependency post installation.
- Headed safety department helping in creating a safe working place for factory employees through sensitization of workers and implementing safety recommendations in line with OSHA.
- Designed various machine components that needed to be purchased both abroad and locally using AutoCAD software. This helped with raising our machine reliability by 5%
- Developed and implemented cost effective maintenance programs and strategies to coding machines, diesel generators, refrigeration and air conditioning equipment, compressed air plants and other facilities which reduced machine breakdowns tremendously.
- Organized maintenance team personnel in carrying out our daily routine maintenance activities which helped maximize throughput, production yields while minimizing on off – specification products.
- Provided leadership, guidance and continuous trainings to technicians and operators enabling them fit into our production and maintenance plans in a reliable and swift manner.

2012

Maintenance Consultant Buy Line Industries Limited

- As a contracted maintenance consultant at Buy line industries limited, I managed to root out problems affecting their injection and blow molding machines.
- I inculcated the culture of preventive maintenance and trained the technical team on root cause analysis of their machine breakdowns which contributed to raising their molding machines availability to over 99% and minimized their off-specification product by 0.0017%.

2012

Data Technician

Geo Maps Africa

 Data collection and entry. I managed to supersede the set records of 40 per day to 60 through forward planning and being organized in my daily collection and entry in the system for the mapped regions.

2010 - 2011 Mechanical Technician Bata Shoe Factory Limited

- Proposed the use of lithium based sticky grease to their open gearing system. This reduced our monthly maintenance cost by 5%
- Attended to machine breakdowns in both tannery and sandak factories on timely basis which ensured machine production dependency was above 90%.
- Carried out yearly overhaul maintenance on the major machines within assigned technical teams.

2008

Industrial Engineering Intern Unilever Tea Kenya Limited

- As a production intern with Unilever Tea Kenya, Mabroukie factory, I designed and assisted in the fabrication of withering trough fan silencers which helped reduce the noise level by about 30%.
- I was tasked with the designing and fabrication of green leaf truck inspection ladder which I managed to complete within the stipulated time.

Educational Qualification

2005 - 2010

Egerton University, Njoro Campus

Bachelor of Science in Manufacturing Engineering and Technology (Second class Honors) I acquired strong background in the following areas:

Product Engineering and quality: Engineering Drawing; Industrial Management; Quality Engineering; Lean Manufacturing; Design and use of jigs, Fixtures and Tooling.

Materials and Processes: Engineering Mechanics; Material Removal and Forming Processes; Casting and Joining Processes; Manufacturing Process Engineering; Thermodynamics

Integration and System Design: Computer Aided Manufacturing; Fluid Mechanics.

2000 – 2003: Alliance High School, Kikuyu

Kenya Certificate of Secondary School Education (A-)

Chairman of Geography club: Tasked with coordination of activities within the club and

reporting status to our patron.

Dormitory Table Leader: Tasked with ensuring that every member of our

dormitory gets a fair and equal share of meals during

mealtimes.

Workshops and trainings

Feb 2020: Training on occupational health and safety conducted at ACI limited

April 2019: Report handling and data analysis using excel conducted by Plant Manager, African

Cotton Industries Limited.

April 2018: Fire Safety Management Training entailing fire prevention, fire protection and fire

preparedness. Conducted by Kenya Red Cross

May 2017: Workshop on Financial Management by Stanford Seed at African Cotton Industries Ltd **April 2017**: Training on financial implications on inefficiencies in our daily operations by Plant

Manager, African Cotton Industries Limited.

Oct 2016: Autonomous Maintenance training organized by plant manager African Cotton Industries

July 2015: Lean Manufacturing organized by Plant Manager African Cotton Industries Ltd. **Sept 2012**: Training on field mapping and data collection by Geo Maps Africa, Kenya

Hobbies

Reading, Swimming, Watching technology documentaries, Research

REFERIES

Mr. Naman Kimathi, Former Plant Manager; African cotton industries Limited: 0726372015

Mr. Mark Amimo; Quality Engineer; AVA Limited, Mombasa, Kenya: 0738744143

Mr. Fulgence M. Sembua, Supply Chain manager; African Cotton Industries Ltd.: 0722688148